A Guide to the Papers of the Eppes-Randolph Families, 1775-1928
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Eppes-Randolph Families 1775-1928
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7109
This collection consists of ca. 50 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased from Howard M. Bradley, Decatur, Ga., 1963 July 8.
Scope and Content
Family correspondence of the Eppes family of Chesterfield County, Va. and Tallahassee, FL. Chief correspondents are: John Wayles Eppes and his wife Mary Eppes, their son Francis Wayles Eppes and his wife Mary Elizabeth Cleland Eppes and their son John Wayles Eppes. Other correspondents include Ezra Bauder, John K. Campbell, and Harriet Randolph.
Of interest is a letter, 1775 July 4, Thomas Jefferson, Philadelphia, to Francis Eppes discussing the battle of Bunker Hill, the death of British major John Pitcairn, and the fitting of New England ships for war.
The collection also includes a letter, 1821 April 5, Ellen Wayles Coolidge, Monticello, to Francis Eppes, Columbia, S. C. regarding Thomas Sully's portrait of Jefferson, a meeting of the University of Virginia Board of Visitors, and a visit of an Englishman. Also, fragments of poetry and hymns, n.d. in the hand of Mary Elizabeth Cleland Eppes; obituaries from newspapers of various members of the Eppes, Bellamy and related families; and deed, 1856 November 20, with plat of Rappanhannock, Va.
Contents List
- [Thomas Jefferson] to [Francis Eppes], 1775 July 4, AL, 1 p. Photocopy; original in Jefferson Papers. (Box 1)
  Discusses the battle of Bunker Hill, the death of British major John Pitcairn, and the fitting of New England ships for war
- M[aria Jefferson] Eppes to John W[ayles] Eppes, 1802 January 21, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with address leaf, docketed; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:1)
  Concerning procuring Umbrella trees, and mentioning a "misfortune that has happen'd at Monticello the burning of the plank house just after it had been completely fill'd with the flooring plank & timber for the cornices."
- M[aria Jefferson] Eppes to John W[ayles] Eppes, [ca. 1802] November 25, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Washington City, November 26; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:2)
  Concerning her desire that her husband see his sons first steps, and asking for enough money to make a return trip.
- M[aria Jefferson] E[ppes] to John W[ayles] Eppes, [ca. 1802?] December 10, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf; docketed; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:3)
  Asking him about his persistent toothache, and her interaction with Mr. Easton Randolph.
- John [Wayles] Eppes to Francis Eppes, 1813 May 24, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:4)
  Containing instruction if Francis "form[s] the company," the need for discipline and regulation, and concerning where Francis should go to school. In his closing, John [Wayles] Eppes mentions "Congress has just met- Mr. Clay of Kentucky is elected speaker."
- John W[ayles] Eppes to Francis Eppes, 1813 December 20, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:5)
  Concerning Francis Eppes' outbreak of measles, and apologizing for his and his mother's not being able to return for Christmas.
- John W[ayles] Eppes to Francis Eppes, [1816] February 10, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:6)
  Concerning the well being of their family, and sending him money.
- John W[ayles] Eppes to Francis Eppes, 1816 February 17, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:7)
  Concerning family matters including the impending death of his aunt Matlida, his recovery from illness, his cousin Wayles' schooling, and containing a list of French books in his possession.
- John [Wayles] Eppes to Francis Eppes, 1818 November 18, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf. (Box-folder 1:8)
  Relating that Gerrardin[e]'s school in Staunton has been recommended for Francis' schooling, and that "this being in a healthy situation and not very distant from Monticello will perhaps meet the approbation of your Grand-papa [Thomas Jefferson]." He continues later, "I could not reconcile to my feelings going in direct opposition to the wishes of your Grand Father and his prejudices against Chappell Hill appear invincible." He instructs Francis to attend to his learning, and that "four years only are left [him] for the acquisition of every thing necessary to render [him] a respectable and useful member of society."
- John [Wayles] Eppes to Francis Eppes, 1818 December 1, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:9)
  Concerning the impending closure of the school Francis attends, and that he "has not heard directly from [Francis'] gran papa [sic; Thomas Jefferson] since [John's] being here- He has never returned answer to the letter [John] sent by [Francis] although through other channels [John] has heard he is out of danger. [Thomas Jefferson] writes occasionally to old Mr. Barnes and to Milligan the book seller in George Town- through Mr. Barnes [John] heard [Thomas Jefferson] had recovered and was able to ride on horse back." Additionally concerning the closure of Mr. Barbour's school, and [Francis'] possible matriculation at Gerrardine's in Staunton, Virginia.
- John [Wayles] Eppes to Francis Eppes, 1818 December 8, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:10)
  Worries that during his school's closure that Francis will lose "some portion of [his] time," and recommends his continual employment in reading history and studying languages. He recommends a history of England, because its history is "much interwoven with that of the United States."
- John [Wayles] Eppes to Francis Eppes, 1819 January 2, ALS, 7 pp. on 4 l.; with address on verso; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:11)
  Instructing him on personal virtue and discipline, recommending integrity, temperance, learning, the proper application of knowledge, and benefiting society.
- [John Wayles Eppes] to Francis Eppes, 1819 May 15, ALS fragment, 2 pp. on 1 l.; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:12)
  Concerning the purchase of a new horse, eating peas, and the importance of managing his time well during this important point in Francis' life.
- John [Wayles] Eppes to Francis Eppes, 1819 June 22, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso; postmarked Richmond, VA, June 29; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:13)
  Concerning his difficulty in sending Francis' books to Richmond, and mentioning harvesting wheat. John also mentions that he will send him cloth to make a homespun coat, and claims, "I have cut off five yards for a coat for you and was very near sending it by mail to your Grand-papa [Thomas Jefferson]- I did not however like to do it without his permission," and instructing him on proper fashion and moral character.
- John [Wayles] Eppes to Francis Eppes, 1819 July 26, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:14)
  Concerning his sending the first three volumes of Berout's [Cours de Mathematiques] on arithmetic, geometry, and algebra, and says that he has not heard anything from either Francis or Francis' grandfather [Thomas Jefferson]. John also mentions that his "family have all been well until now-[they] have a Negroe boy (Henry) who has not been entirely clear of fever for eight or ten days" and fears that it has the "same character [as] the fever which gave [them] so much trouble last year." Additionally, he wonders why Francis does not room with or speak of his cousin Wayles.
- Miss H[arriet Randolph] to [Mrs. Francis Eppes], 182[0] December 5, AL, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; postmarked Norfolk, VA, December 7; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:15)
  Concerning her passion for a newly constructed ship, the North Carolina, in Norfolk, its immense dimensions, and concerning a party she attended on board.
- Ellen Wayles Randolph to Francis Eppes, 1821 April 5, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:16)
  Thanking him for his prompt reply to her letter, defending male gallantry, and expostulating on the inadequacy of writing when compared to speech. Mentions the recent guests at Monticello for the "meeting of the Visitors of the University [of Virginia]." Additionally, discusses the recent departure of [Thomas] Sully "the great portrait painter" who has been commissioned by the West Point Academy to paint a portrait of Grand papa [Thomas Jefferson], and commending his work, stating, "the upper part of the face is perfect, the eye is so full of life that you almost expect to see it roll. He is the first painter who has ever succeeded in catching the expression of Grandpapa's countenance, and rendering that mixture of dignity & benevolence which prevail in it. If the copy is as good as the original (for a full length portrait is required, and Sully carried away with him simply the head and neck on a small bit of canvas) it will probably be the best representation existing of one to whom further ages must look back with gratitude and admiration. This portrait is defective about the mouth & skin, but the painter seems to be aware of this defect, and will endeavor to correct it." She later mentions that "Grandpapa is well and as usual intent on the University [of Virginia], [which]? will be ready for you I dare say in eighteen years if you care [for a little]? delay, or maybe in seven-in good truth, I do not believe those 'potent grave and reverend signors,' the Visitors, know themselves when this great work is to go into operation."
- Miss H[arriet] Randolph to Mrs. Francis Eppes, 1825 March 2, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:17)
  Concerning the health of family members, the unnatural amount of precipitation, Franklin Randloph's visit, and other family matters.
- Miss Harriet [Randolph] to Mrs. Francis Eppes, 1826 June 18, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:18)
  Concerning her travels with their mother, and other family matters.
- H[arriet Randolph] to Mrs. Francis Eppes, 1827 September 6, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; with wax seal; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:19)
  Regarding her anxiety about a fever among Elizabeth's slaves, yet stating, "I know it is contrary to experience to suppose that a fever of this kind beginning among the negroes will extend to the white family." Also concerning the preoccupation of the ladies with which she is acquainted with marriage, but claims "for my part, I am more thoroughly disgusted with mankind at this time than I ever was before and the 'blessed estate of matrimony' never stood before me so openly in its deformity." She also details the situation at Monticello, where most of the furniture has been removed, and that "the house is really like a great hotel and the impertinence of people is beyond endurance." She later continues, "You have no idea how desolate the old place looks. The lawn is quite grown up with weeds and young trees, and the whole establishment has a wild untended appearance which is quite melancholy. Within doors all has changed. The girls occupy but a corner of the house, and that corner without furniture, and without servants. There really are not persons to carry on the business of a family, and I forsee trouble without end to Virginia [Jefferson Randolph]."
- Mrs. M. E. R. Eppes to Miss Mary Eppes, 1828 August 24, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; postmarked Lynchburg, VA, September 8; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:20)
  Allaying her fears that a fever rages in Lynchburg, but laments the harsh weather and poor crop growth there, and the possibility of her removal to Florida. Also mentioning the "revival of religion" in Lynchburg and elsewhere.
- John K. Campbell to "Elizabeth," 1828 September 18, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; postmarked Lipona, Florida; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:21)
  Concerning consulting in her behalf with others "as to the probable success of a female seminary," and informs her that an academy in Quincy, Florida, Gadsen County is about to open and is "the most eligible situation."
- John [Wayles] Eppes to Francis Eppes (with a postscript signed J. B. Ferguson on verso dated 1840 February 20), [1840 February 18], ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:22)
  Concerning his studies, and his desire to see his father in the summer. The postscript by Ferguson assures Francis that his sons are both excellent students, and that in his absence, Ferguson and his wife will be parents to them.
- E[zra] Bauder to Unidentified, 1856 September 3, Printed letter, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:23)
  Detailing the wages and duties of agents selling subscriptions for shares in "200 Farms and 10,000 Building Lots for sale in the Gold Region of Virginia," with a handwritten note by Bauder on the verso.
- Indenture: John W[ayles] Eppes with Ezra Bouder, 1856 November 20, DS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with envelope. (Box-folder 1:24)
  For a plot of land in the first section of the Rappahannock Town Plat.
- Map of the Gold Mining District of Virginia, [1856] (Box-folder 1:25)
  Original cataloged separately as: Broadside 1856 .B37
- Charles W. Ward to Editor of The Churchman, 1881 May 31, TL copy, 3 pp. on 3 l. (Box-folder 1:26)
  Concerning Francis Eppes' recent burial, and his attachment to his grandfather, Thomas Jefferson.
- Miss Fanny Burke to "Dear Josie," 1928 March 20, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:27)
  Concerning the authenticity of a handwritten letter of Thomas Jefferson's, and a "monochrome medallion portrait" of the same.
- Harriet [Randolph] to Mrs. Francis Eppes, n.y. March 19, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; with wax seal; postmarked Charlottesville, VA, March 20; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:28)
  Regarding James' recovery from a fever through Dr. Gilmer's management despite the fact that she had thought of James as already dead.
- J. Burton Harrison to Francis Eppes, n.y. August 3, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; docketed; postmarked Lynchburg, VA, August 3; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:29)
  Concerning traveling through Germany, Switzerland, France, Italy, and Austria, and discussing the English disregard for poetry.
- F[rancis] Eppes to J[ohn] W[ayles] Eppes, n.d., ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; address on verso. (Box-folder 1:30)
  Requesting to borrow a wagon.
- John Wayles Eppes to Francis Eppes, n.d., ALS fragment, 1 p. on 1 l; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:31)
  Appears to be a portion of an instructive letter to his son.
- Envelope addressed to Lieutenant John W[ayles] Eppes, [ca. 1861-1865] (Box-folder 1:32)
  Postmarked Tallahassee, FL, October 28.
- Address Leaf: John [Wayles] Eppes to Francis Eppes, n.d., 1 item; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:33)
- Portion of an Anglican religious printed volume, [ca. 1764]?, Printed pamphlet, 39 pp. (Box-folder 1:34)
  Containing sundry prayers and exegeses including: "Forms of prayer to be used at sea," "A form of prayer with thanksgiving" concerning the Gunpowder plot, "A form of prayer and fasting" for the day of martyrdom of Charles I, "A form of prayer with thanksgiving" concerning the Restoration, "A form of prayer with thanksgiving" for the day King George [III] assumed the throne, along with "The Articles of Religion."
- Hymns in the handwriting of Mary E. R. Eppes, 1829 May 15 to August 2, AMsS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:35)
  Containing the hymns "Like Noah's weary dove," "How blest the tie that binds," "When gathering clouds around I view," and "But the poor shall not always be forgotten," and with annotations concerning Mary's first encounter with each.
- Receipt from Thomas E. Randolph to Francis Eppes, 1836 May 2, ADS, 1 p.; endorsed on verso; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:36)
  For payment of "monies collected by him for the church fund."
- Poetry Fragments in Mary E. R. Eppes's hand, n.d., AMsS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; Barrow. (Box-folder 1:37)
- Dipping Needle Description, n.d., ANs, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:38)
- Essay on God's Justice, n.d., AMs, 6 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:39)
  An exegesis on Genesis 28:12, and concerning the Old Testament's inclusion of the Old Testament Saints' faults and crimes.
- Calling Card of Mrs. Marion Howard Bradley, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 1:40)
- Francis Eppes' Obituary [from Orange County, Florida], 1881, Newspaper clipping, 1 item. (Box-folder 1:41)
- "Remains of Thomas Jefferson," 1882 June 4, Newspaper clipping, 1 item. (Box-folder 1:42)
- Major Burton W. Bellamy's Obituary, n.d., Newspaper clipping, 1 item. (Box-folder 1:43)
- Mrs. Josephine H. Eppes' Obituary, n.d., Newspaper clipping, 1 item. (Box-folder 1:44)
- Thomas Jefferson Eppes' Obituary, n.d., Newspaper clipping, 1 item. (Box-folder 1:45)
- Anita Bellamy Paul's Obituary, n.y. November 13, Newspaper clipping, 1 item. (Box-folder 1:46)
- Mrs. Anita Bellamy Paul's Obituary, n.d., Newspaper clipping, 1 item. (Box-folder 1:47)
- Mary Page Randolph's Obituary, n.d., Newspaper clipping, 1 item. (Box-folder 1:48)
- Letter Fragments, n.d., AL. 2 fragments. (Box-folder 1:49)
  One in Jefferson's hand.